Welcome to the eLearning
session, Ensemble: HL7 Custom
欢迎来到 eLearning 课程，
Schemas.
Ensemble HL7 用户自定义 Schemas。
For Ensemble or HealthShare to
properly parse an HL7 message,
在 Ensemble 或者 HealthShare 中，
为了解析一个 HL7 消息，
it must be assigned
a schema category,
必须要有一个合适色 schema 类，
for example 2.5, and a document
type, for example ORU_R01.
比如 2.5, 和一文档类型，比如 ORU_R01。
With this information, Ensemble
can validate a message against
有了这些信息，Ensemble 可以根据
the schema, and can parse
a property path such
schema 校验消息，解析属性路径，
as MSH:CountryCode.
比如 MSH:CountryCode。
Data Transformation
Language, Routing Rules,
数据转换语言，路由规则，
and custom Caché Object
Script parsing rely heavily
以及用户的 Caché 的对象脚本解析都
on the schema category and
document type assignments.
依赖于指定的 schema 类，和文档类型。
Ensemble comes with
all HL7 version 2.1
Ensemble 自带所有的 HL7 版本，
through 2.7 schema
definitions installed.
从 2.1 到 2.7 schema 的定义。
Schema version 2.7.1 will
be included in the 2014.1
Schema 版本 2.7.1 包含在
release of Ensemble.
Ensemble 2014.1 中。
Using a standard HL7 schema,
custom schemas can be created.
利用一个标准的 HL7 schemas, 用户可以创建一个自定义的 schemas。
A custom schema can
modify existing structures
用户自定义 schema 可以修改现有的结构
or add additional structures.
或则增加额外的结构。
Only the alterations need be
defined in a custom schema.
所有的变动，只需要定义一个用户 schema。
Let's take a look at
a simple Production
让我们在 Ensemble 门户中
in the Ensemble Portal.
看一下一个简单的 Production.
So we will go to Ensemble,
Configure, Production,
我们到 Ensemble 配置，Production,
and we are looking at the
eLearning.SchemaProduction.
我们看到有个 eLearning.SchemaProduction。
If we take a look at the
Business Service FromLab,
如果我们看一下 Business Service FromLab,
we can see that the Message
Schema Category is 2.5.
我们可以看到其消息 Schema Category 是 2.5。
This means that all messages
received by this Business
这意味着，所有经由这 Business Service
Service will be assigned a
Message Schema Category of 2.5.
接受的消息的 Schema Category 指定为 2.5。
The document type will be
based on the content of MSH:9.
文档类型由 MSH:9 的内容决定。
Messages created by Data
Transformation Language
由数据转换语言创建的消息
will take their Message Schema
Category and document type
会从 DTL 的定义中获取消息的
from the definition of the DTL.
Schema Category 和文档类型。
If you create an HL7 message
and Caché Object Script,
如果你由 Caché 对象脚本创建了一个 HL7 消息，
you should set these
properties appropriately.
你应该设置相应的这些属性。
Let's process a message
through this Production.
让我们在这个 Production 中处理一个消息。
We first need to
start the Production,
首先我们需要启动这个 Production，
and then we need
to put the message
然后我们需要放一些消息
into the appropriate directory.
到合适的目录下。
We've already saved
one to our clipboard,
我们已经通过剪贴板保存了一个，
so I just need to paste
it into the directory
所以我只需要将其放入一个目录，
to be processed
by the Production.
其将由这个 Production 来处理。
Returning to our Production,
we can examine the messages
返回到我们的 Production, 我们检查一下
processed by this Production.
会被 Production 处理的消息。
So we go to the
Messages tab, and we'll
我们去 Messages 标签页，我们
go to the Message Viewer.
会来到 "Message Viewer"。
We're only looking
at the message that
我们只看发送自
was sent from the
From_Lab Business Service
to the From_Lab_Router.
到 From_Lab_Router 的消息。
By choosing this message,
and selecting Contents
选中这个消息，
in our Message
Viewer, we can see
并在 Message View 中选择Contents (内容)
all of the contents
of our message,
我们可以看到这消息的所有内容。
and see the full HL7 message.
并且可以看到整个 HL7 消息。
By viewing full contents,
it's easier to read
通过查看整个内容，方便阅读，
and we can see that there
is an error in this message,
我们也可以看到这个消息间有个错误，
because there's a z-segment
that is unrecognized.
因为有个 z-segment 不能被辨认。
We can also see that the
z-segment in the message
但是我们也可以看到消息中这 z-segment
contents itself is in black,
while the others are blue.
的内容是黑色的，而其它则为蓝色。
At the top of our message,
we can see that we have
在消息的头部，我们可以看到
our document type 2.5:ORU_R01,
colon ORU underscore R01,
我们的文档类型是 2:5:ORU_R01,
冒号，ORU,下划线 R01,
and a document type
category of 2.5.
以及文档类型为 2.5.
So let's create a custom
schema and add the ZPI segment
所以让我们来创建一个用户 schema，并加入一个 ZPI 片段，
so we can process this message.
因而我们可以处理这消息。
Before we actually create
a custom schema to resolve
在我们真正创建一个用户 schema 来
the error, let's examine the 2.5
schema in the Ensemble portal.
解决这个错误前，我们先在 Ensemble 门户中查看一下 schema 2.5.
So we will go back to
the Ensemble Portal
因此，我们来到 Ensemble 门户
to interoperate, HL7 and
choose Schema Structures.
菜单 interoperate, HL7,并选择 "Schema Structures".
From Ensemble release
2013.1 and on,
在 Ensemble 中，从版本 2013.1 开始，
you can create and
maintain HL7 schemas
你可以在管理门户中创建
in the management portal.
和维护 HL7 schemas。
Prior to 2013.1,
custom schemas had
在版本 2013.1之前，用户 schemas,
to be created and
maintained in Studio.
只能在 Studio 中创建和维护。
When we select the 2.5 schema,
you can see the Message Types.
当我们选择了 schema 2.5, 你可以看到消息类型。
You can drill into each
to see more information.
你可以深入下去，看到更多信息。
The message structure is
separate from the message type,
消息结构独立于消息类型，
and message types may
share the same structure.
但消息类型可能共有相同的结构。
So let's examine the
ORU_R01 Message Type,
让我们察看一下 ORU_R01 消息类型，
and the Message Structure
is also ORU_R01.
和有同样名字的 ORU_R01 消息结构。
If we drill down to
the Message Structure,
我们可深入到消息的结构中，
when you look at the
Message Structure
当你看消息结构时，
you can see whether segments
are optional or repeating.
你可以看什么片段是可选的或者是重复的。
You can also see that there
are groups of segments
你也可看到这里有片段组
that are repeated together.
可以组织在一起重复发生。
If we look at the
Segment Structure,
让我们看一下片段的结构，
we can see all of the
Fields for that Segment.
你可以看到片段上的所有字段。
We can also examine Data
Structures and Code Tables
我们也可以查看数据结构和代码标，
as they are defined
for the 2.5 schema.
它们也定义在 schema 2.5 中。
More information
about Data Structures
更多关于数据结构的信息
is available in Ensemble
2014.1, and can be
可以在 Ensemble 2014.1 中可得，
used for additional validation.
可用来做外加的校验。
At the top of our
page, there are
在我们这页的头部，有个
buttons that will allow
you to add a New schema,
按钮，可允许你添加新的 schema,
or to Export or Import a schema.
或则导出/导入一个 schema.
While the standard
schemas cannot be edited,
虽然标准 schemas 是不能被编辑的，
we can create a new one
based on an existing schema.
我们可以根据现有的 schema 创建一个新的。
By clicking New, we can
create a custom schema.
点击"New",我们可以创建一用户 schema。
A custom schema can contain
Message Types, Structures,
在用户 schema 中可包含消息类型，结构，
Segments, and so forth.
片段等等。
If a Message Type's
segment or other item
如果一个消息类型的片段或其它项目
is not explicitly defined
in the custom schema,
在用户 schema 中没有明确地定义，
it is found in the base class,
in a manner analogous to object
可以在基类中找到，这和对象的继承
inheritance.
相类似。
So let's create a
new custom schema,
让我们来创建一个新的用户 schema，
and we will use 2.5
as our base schema,
我们会用 2.5 作为 schema 的基类，
and our new schema will
be called eLearning_2.5.
所以我们的新 schema 称之为 eLearning_2.5。
And as you can see,
it has been added
你可以看到它同它的基类一样
to the list of
schemas with its base,
被加入到 schemas 的列表中，
and it is not a standard
schema, meaning that we can now
并且不是一个标准 schema,意味着我们可以
edit this schema.
编辑这个 schema。
So in our tabs, we
have the ability
所以在我们的标签页中，我们可以
of creating new Message Types,
Document Type Structures and so
创建新的消息类型，文档类型结构等等，
forth, or copying an existing
message type from the base.
或者可以从现有的基类中复制消息类型。
All we need to add are the
items that are different.
我们所需要的是加入不同的项目。
I will start with the
Segment Structures,
我会从片段结构开始，
and add a new z-segment.
加入一个新的 z-segment。
I can add the new
segment from scratch,
我可以从头开始加入一个片段，
and add the fields one
by one, or I can base it
然后一个个地加入字段，或者我可以根据
on an existing segment.
一个现有的片段加入。
We will copy from base
the P-I-D segment,
我们从基类中复制一个 PID 片段，
and call our new segment
Z-P-I. At this point,
并且称这个新的片段为 ZPI。到目前为止，
I can change any of the fields
from our standard P-I-D segment
我可以在标准的 PID 片段中修改任何字段
to accommodate the requirements
of my custom Z-P-I segment.
一适应我的用户 ZPI 片段的要求。
I can also add or delete
fields as required.
根据需求，我可以增加或删除字段。
So let's save our
new Z-P-I segment
让我们保存我们的新 ZPI 片段，
so that we can add the segment
to a custom message type
所以我们可以增添这个片段到
based on ORU_R01.
基于 ORU_R01 的用户消息类型。
Because I want to customize
the structure of the ORU_R01
因为我要客户化 ORU_R01 消息结构，
message, I need to add both the
Message Type and the Message
我需要添加消息类型和消息
Structure.
结构。
I can do this in one step by
going to the Message Type tab,
我可以在 "Message Type" 标签页中，
Copy From Base, and the Message
Type to copy is ORU_R01.
"copy From Base" 选择 ORU_R01 复制消息类型。
If we have the box checked
for "Create this message
如果我们选中 "Create this message Structure" 选框，
structure", if the Message
Structure doesn't exist
那么如果消息结构不存在的话，
it will be created along
with the Message Type
消息结构会随着消息类型一起被创建。
when we click OK.
点击 OK.
By going to the
Document Type Structure,
到文档类型结构(Document Type Structure)
we can see that we have indeed
created the structure along
我们可以看到我们真的创建了结构
with the type.
和类型。
By clicking on our
Document Type Structure,
点中我们的文档类型结构，
we see that our
custom structure is
我们可以看到我们的用户结构
identical to the base
structure because we have not
和基结构是一模一样的，因为我们还
made any changes yet.
没有做任何改变。
We will add the Z-P-I segment
to the end of this structure.
我们会在这结构的尾部增加一个 ZPI 片段。
Since this is a
custom structure,
因为这是一个用户结构
we have the Edit
button at the top.
我们在头部有个 "Edit" 按钮。
So let's click
Edit so that we can
所以让我们来点击 "Edit", 我们可以
make the appropriate changes.
作相应的修改。
As you can see that
the raw definition uses
正如你所见的那样，原始的定义
the same convention
that is used in studio.
使用同 studio 中相同的惯例。
The square brackets
mean optional,
方括号意味着可选，
and these squiggle
brackets mean repeating.
大括号意味着可重复。
You can also use angle
brackets for choices.
你也可以用尖括号表示选择。
So I will add the Z-P-I segments
to the end of this message,
我在消息尾部加入这个 ZPI 片段，
and all elements must
be separated by a tilde.
所有的元素必须用波浪符分割。
So by typing tilde Z-P-I at
the end of my raw definition,
所以原始定义的尾部，输入波浪符，ZPI，
I can add the Z-P-I segment
to my message structure,
我可以加 ZPI 片段到我的消息结构，
and I'll click Save,
and the new structure
我点击 "Save", 然后这个新的结构
will be reflected to the right.
就被反映在右边的列表中了。
And as you can see,
the Z-P-I segment
正如你所见，这个 ZPI 片段
has been added to the
end of my structure.
被加到了我的结构的尾部。
I want the Z-P-I segment to
be optional because it may not
我要 ZPI 片段是可选的，因为它不一定
always be in the message.
存在在所有的消息中。
So I need to change
my raw definition
所以我需要修改我的原始定义，
to make this an optional
segment by adding square bracket
加入方括号，使得这片段是可选的，
and tilde before Z-P-I,
and tilde, square bracket
在 ZPI 前后，添加波浪符和方括号，
after Z-P-I. I will
save my definition,
保存我的定义，
examine my structure to
make sure it reflects
检查一下我的结构，保证所有我做的修改
what I have done, and click OK.
体现出来了，然后点击 OK。
My custom structure now
contains the Z-P-I segment.
现在，我的用户结构含有 ZPI 片段。
Message Structures
and Segment Structures
消息结构和片段结构是
are the most common
items to change,
常被修改的项目，
but you can also edit Data
Types and Code Tables.
但你也可以修改数据类型和代码表。
So now I will return to
my Ensemble Production.
现在我回到我的 Ensemble Production 页面。
I will stop the Production, and
modify the From_Lab Business
我停止我的 Production，然后修改 Business Service
Service to use my custom schema
instead of the standard one.
From_Lab，采用我的用户 schema，以替换标准的。
I'll apply my changes, start the
Production again, and process
应用这修改，重起 Production, 并且
my message once again.
再次处理我的消息。
Let's examine the
messages again.
让我们再次检查消息，
We'll choose the new one
that has been processed,
我们选择一个已经被处理过的，
View Full Contents, and we can
now see that there is no error
选 "View Full Contents", 我们可以看到这里没有任何错误
and the Z-P-I segment
is now in blue
并且 ZPI 片段现在是蓝色，
like the rest of our segments.
如果其余的片段一样。
All other segments are
processed correctly
所有的片段被正确地处理了，
because we haven't made any
changes to them in our custom
因为我们还没有在我们的用户 schema
schema.
中作其它的修改。
We do not want to reject
messages for most HL7 routing
我们不希望，只是因为消息与 schema 不匹配
productions simply because they
don't exactly match the schema.
而拒绝大部分从 HL7 路由 productions 来的消息。
Business Rules or
Data Transformations
Business 规则或是数据转换
will only check
particular fields
只检查特定的字段，
that are known to be required
by the target system.
这需要目标系统来实现。
In some circumstances, you may
want to validate the message
在某些情况下，你可能希望这些
structure in different ways.
消息结构能有不同的方式来校验。
Prior to 2014.1, it was
only possible to validate
2014.1 以前，只能校验
that Ensemble recognized
a valid HL7 message,
Ensemble 所能辨识的有效的 HL7 消息，
and that the segments
matched the schema.
而且该片段和 schema 能匹配。
This validation
could be controlled
这中校验能在
using the d, m, and z values
to the message router.
消息路由处通过 d,m,z 所控制。
If the message
failed validation,
如果消息校验失败，
it was sent to the
bad message handler.
会被发送到坏消息处理器。
In 2014.1, it is possible to do
further validation, including
在2014.1, 可以做进一步的校验，包括
checking that required
fields are present,
检查必填字段是否存在，
checking fields
match the data type,
所检查的字段是否和数据类型匹配，
and validating field values
are consistent with code table
所校验的字段值是否和代码表
definitions.
的定义相符。
This is specialist
functionality designed
这些专门的功能是为了人们
for people building
clearinghouses
构建资讯交流所，或是
or similar applications.
相类似的应用所设计。
Many more flags are available
to control validation,
还有很多标志可以用来控制校验，
and the message can be
validated programmatically
并且消息利用校验方法和
with the validate method
of an HL7 message object.
HL7 消息对象进行程序化地校验。
Thank you for watching
the eLearning session
谢谢您收看 eLearning 课程
Ensemble: HL7 Custom Schemas.
Ensemble HL7 用户自定义 Schemas.